Cutting an essential nutrient doesn't
sound very healthy, hence the word
essential. But don't worry, you won't
have to suffer a slow death just to
achieve a supercharged metabolism. And
I'm not kidding, supercharge is the
correct word because as the data shows,
it's really a huge increase in a short
period of time. In fact, the nutrient
that I'm talking about is protein. And
if you're thinking to yourself, "Wait a
minute, aren't high protein diets
supposed to help with fat loss and all
that jazz?" Yeah, that's what past
research shows. And while we're going in
the exact opposite direction, I'll show
you how both can be true. Both low and
high protein can melt body fat. But this
way, you can eat even more. Okay, let's
get into it. This is going to fascinate
you. In this study, researchers put
people on a low protein diet and
compared against a higher protein diet
in the same individuals over just five
weeks on one diet and five weeks on the
other. Pretty simple design, right?
During this time, the researchers were
tightly controlling body weight. They
wanted body weight to remain stable. We
actually see that here. Body weight is
on the vertical axis and the low protein
is the blue ticker there for about five
weeks. And then the participants
switched to a higher protein diet, the
gray ticker there. As you can clearly
see, body weight remained completely
stable. Here's where the intriguing part
comes in, the supercharging that I've
been promising you. If we look at the
consumption, remember to maintain
weight. We see the data here. It's the
same general organization as the body
weight data, just that the food
consumption is on the vertical axis. We
also see the bar graph showing the same
thing in a condensed format. Notice how
the low protein diet led to an increase
in food consumption and the high protein
diet led to a restabilization of intake.
So they maintained weight but ate more.
Incredible. But to put this in context,
they were able to eat 20% more calories,
about a 600 calorie increase in just
five weeks. Now, I want you to think if
you just maintained your nutrition
except dropped your protein lower, that
means for the same amount of food, you
begin losing body fat. How crazy cool is
that? Okay, but an obvious question is
if they increase their activity
throughout that time, their expenditure
increased. The answer is no. As seen
here, it's flat across the board.
Obviously, you'd then assume that their
metabolism increased over those weeks,
especially considering what we're
discussing. But the reality is there was
no change in resting metabolism. So,
what's up with the title and what's up
with their ability to eat so much more?
People are eating more, moving the same
amount, no change in metabolism, yet
they aren't gaining weight. How? Well,
it comes down to a protein your body
produces called FGF-21 or fibroblast
growth factor 21. It's a hormone because
it's secreted into the bloodstream and
interacts with the tissues of your body.
We'll get into certain aspects in just a
bit, but for now, we get some idea that
FGF-21 is implicated here because if we
look at the short-term experiments
looking at a low protein meal versus a
higher protein meal, we can see the blue
line indicating the low protein and the
black line indicating the higher
protein. Over the hours of each meal,
FGF-21 levels rise only in the low
protein meal. Now if we look at the same
measurement time in a measure of
metabolism, there is an increase in the
low protein condition. So this means
that when the researchers are measuring
resting metabolism over the 5 weeks,
there's no change. But when measuring
over the course of a few hours postmeal,
there's an increase over the higher
protein condition. In addition, this
change associates with increased FGF-21.
But that's only half the story because
we don't actually know if it's FGF-21
directly that's causing this and we also
don't know how it works. Well, we don't
yet. But the researchers took steps to
find out. So, what did they find and how
they find it? This is where they turned
to mice. Don't worry, we'll be returning
to the human species soon enough. But in
mice, they generated global FGF21
knockout mice, meaning that these mice
are incapable of generating FGF-21. Now,
since the researchers suspect FGF-21 of
causing these wonderful changes, we'd
expect that these mice to not experience
the increased food consumption yet the
lack of weight gain. So, if we pop open
those data here, we're looking at wild
type mice. cell mice that are still able
to generate FGF-21. And we see the two
low protein diets and the usually higher
protein diet in gray. As expected, body
weight remains stable just like in the
human data. However, the food intake was
markedly greater for the low protein
conditions. Again, in line with the
human research. Now, if we add the
FGF-21 knockout mice, we see their food
intake gets knocked back down as their
weight remains stable. To be honest, I
would have liked to have seen some
metabolism measures, but at least we're
seeing the feeding effect from knocking
out FGF-21. But it doesn't end there
because the researchers related this
back to humans. In fact, we're not just
going to cover more of the human data,
but we'll also go over what is
considered low protein without causing
health issues while still getting the
benefits this study outlines. But before
we get to that, there's also another
study that covers specific components.
amino acids in protein and how not all
amino acids may need to be reduced
depending on the amino acid profile as
well as a mystery related to FGF-21. I'm
covering that along with if you could do
this on a high carbohydrate or highfat
diet and the exact measurement of low
protein for your body in the extended
edition of this video that you're
watching. It's of course included with
the physionic insiders link is in the
description along with you know all my
other analyses, private podcast, live
sessions with me and much more. Again to
join just use the link in the
description. I hope to see you there in
the final experiment before we tie this
all together. The researchers did a
proteomics analysis which means that
they took fat samples from all the
participants either on the low protein
or higher protein diet. Then they
measure the various functional proteins
that the cells have created. Think you
know enzymes, structural proteins and so
on. They then compare the numbers of
these proteins between the fat from the
low protein group and the fat acquired
from the high protein group. Here's what
they saw. This is a volcano plot because
it looks like it's going boom like a
volcano. Scientists and data analysts
have simple minds at times. I appreciate
it. That line running down the middle
indicates an effect has been detected
statistically. The values falling to the
left of the explosion indicate reduced
levels of these functional proteins
within the fat cells. And the ones to
the right of the boom indicate increased
levels. I know this means nothing to you
yet, but there's a fascinating discovery
here. Many of the proteins on the right
side, the ones that are more abundant on
the low protein diet, are related to
specific important mitochondrial
proteins. Then several of the ones on
the left, so reduce concentration are
another mitochondrial protein. So why
this split and why mitochondria?
Mitochondria,
should I say it or are you going to say
it? Okay, I'll just do this.
are organels inside many of your cells
that produce the majority of the
cellular energy throughout the mass
production of adenosine triphosphate or
ATP for short. The proteins that are
increased in the low protein diet are
part of the chain of proteins called the
electron transport chain. And these
proteins are critical for the end result
energy generation. Now, ATP generation,
since mitochondria have two membranes,
they pump protons into the middle space
between the two membranes. That's
important because those protons use the
terminal protein, the ATP synthes, to
pour back into the intersections of the
mitochondria. And when they pour in,
they rotate the ATP synthes, allowing it
to generate ATP. So, think of it like a
watermill. The protons are the water and
the wheel is the ATP synthes. And then
obviously the proteins of the electron
transport chain sigh in annoyance at the
ATP synthes and begin pumping those
protons back to where they belong. It's
a feudal cycle. Anyway, that's all tied
to food consumption as you'll soon see.
But remember, there was a split in the
mitochondrial proteins. Most increased,
but some were reduced. those that were
reduced make up the ATP synthes that we
just discussed. So why would the fat
cells produce more of the electron
transport chain proteins yet make less
of the ATP synthes proteins? I mean they
work together. What's the deal here?
Well, the protons need to keep moving
from the middle to the intersection of
the mitochondria. The cell has other
ways of accomplishing that, like
producing what's known as an uncoupling
protein or UCP for short. The
researchers hypothesized the
mitochondrian have more uncoupling
proteins, which creates an opening for
protons to pour through, but since
they're pouring through those proteins,
they aren't producing ATP. This, of
course, can't stand because the cell
dies with no energy. So the cell uses
more substrate to energize the electron
transport chain to keep pumping protons
to allow some of the protons to go
through the limited ATP synthes even in
spite of the increased leaking going on
through the uncoupling proteins. This
all relates to food because the
substrate comes from the food you eat,
the fats and the carbohydrates that you
consume and get biochemically met
metabolized to mitochondrial substrate
that feeds this electron transport
chain. So in short, the more UCP, the
greater the inefficiency of mitochondria
and the greater the inefficiency, the
more substrate, i.e. food or fat
molecules from your fat cells needed to
be metabolized to keep cellular ATP
levels constant. Unfortunately, here is
where I think the study falls a bit
short. While yes, this is a hypothesis
and yes, it's been shown in other
studies looking at other physiological
processes, they fail to prove that this
is the mechanism in this study. In fact,
the researchers acknowledged that the
uncoupling protein was not increased in
the proteomics data that we just went
over a bit ago. In addition, they
supplied no biochemical data to prove
their hypothesis correct. So, while it's
a possible mechanism and explanation, I
should point out that it's just a
possibility, not proven. But none of
that negates the actual outcomes that we
saw. People eating much more yet not
gaining weight. So, how should we think
about all this? Well, I'd be remiss not
to mention a few things like the fact
that this is still a small study and
only studied young men. I think there
are inherent risks to reducing protein
too low for those over the age of 60. In
addition, none of the participants are
engaging in strenuous activity, which
has a tremendous impact on protein
requirements. That said, for the
majority of others, the researchers
actually used a protein level that yes
is quite low, but still above the health
standard. So there's no need to
completely deprive oneself of protein,
an act of sure fatality. I'd also like
to add that there are many
recommendations to increase protein for
fat loss and overall health. And those
recommendations can still remain true
while this study exists. It isn't either
or. In fact, simply exploring a
different way to achieve the same
results. You could use a high protein
diet and take its advantages like
increased satiety and improved exercise
recovery or you could go a lower protein
approach that stimulates metabolism
instead. They both lead to the same end
just by different paths. Okay, so what
do we take away from this one? A low
protein diet defined as 9% of total
calories could be a viable option for
fat loss and stimulating your
metabolism. You'd calculate that by
using the following calculation. Keep in
mind that the caveats I mentioned
earlier, it's not for everyone. Two,
this low protein diet has these
physiological effects through the
molecule FGF-21. Although there are
still questions about the exact
mechanisms that it functions through. I
think one of the issues with low protein
diets though is that there just isn't
much meat on the bone. You know, unlike
this next video, which is equivalent to
like a juicy ribeye, or if you're not
into meat, then a juicy tempe, uh,
quinoa, black bean bowl, I don't know,
something to that